[音乐播放]
[MUSIC PLAYING]
DAVID MALAN: 这是 CS50的 Python 编程入门。
DAVID MALAN: This is CS50's Introduction to Programming with Python.
我的名字是大卫 · 马兰，本周我们将关注条件句。
My name is David Malan, and this week we focus on conditionals.
条件语句，或者条件语句，在 Python 和其他语言中,
Conditionals, or conditional statements, in Python and in other languages,
问问题和回答问题的能力
are this ability to ask questions and answer those questions, in order
来决定是否执行这行代码？
to decide do you want to execute this line of code?
还是这行代码？
Or this line of code?
还是另一行代码？
Or this other line of code instead?
他们允许你在道路上走岔路,
They allow you to take the proverbial forks in the road,
在你自己的代码里，逻辑上。
within your own code, logically.
那么，我们该如何做出这些决定呢？
So how might we go about making some of these decisions?
事实证明 Python 有很多内置语法。
Well, it turns out that Python comes with a lot of built-in syntax.
例如，这里只是一些符号
For instance, here are just some of the symbols
您可以在 Python 中使用它来提问。
you can use in Python to ask questions.
不可否认，这是数学问题，但是我们可以从这里开始，如果可以的话
Admittedly, mathematical questions, but we'll start there, if only
使示例尽早保持简单。
to keep the examples simple early on.
第一个符号，你们可能从数学中知道，代表大于。
This first symbol, as you might know from math, represents greater than.
第二个符号可能看起来不太熟悉，因为我们通常是这样写的
The second symbol might not look too familiar, because we usually write it
就像一张纸上的东西。
all as one thing on a piece of paper.
但在键盘上，如果你想说大于等于,
But on a keyboard, if you want to say greater than or equal to,
你会用这个符号代替。
you'd use this symbol instead.
当然，这意味着小于。
This, of course, means less than.
这意味着小于或等于。
This means less than or equal to.
这个有点奇怪。
And this one's a bit of a curiosity.
我们在函数和变量中看到,
We've seen, in our look at functions and variables,
我们如何能够使用一个单一的等号赋值给变量。
how we were able to assign values to variables using a single equal sign.
但那个等号并不代表等号。
But that equal sign didn't represent equality.
它代表从右到左的分配。
It represented assignment, from right to left.
那太好了，因为它解决了那个问题。
That's great, because it solved that problem.
但这让我们陷入了困境，因为我们现在
But it left us in a bit of a bind, because how do we now
比较两样东西，左边和右边？
compare two things, left and right?
在 Python 和许多语言中，实际上使用了两个相等的边。
Well, in Python, and in many languages, you actually use two equal sides.
两个相等的符号代表相等，比较这个东西
So two equal signs represents equality, comparing the thing
在左边和右边。
on the left and the right.
一个等号一如既往地代表赋值,
One equal sign, as always, represents assignment,
从右到左复制东西。
copying the thing from the right to the left.
最后，最后一个符号表示不等于。
Lastly, this last symbol represents not equal to.
所以这个叹号或者 bang 后面跟着一个等号,
So the exclamation point, or bang, followed by an equal sign,
意味着不等于它旁边的某个值。
means not equal to some value next to it.
用这些符号或其他符号来问问题,
Well, to ask the questions using these symbols, or any others,
我们需要 Python 中的另一个关键字。
we're going to need another keyword in Python.
这个关键词，很简单，就像英语一样，是 if。
And that keyword, quite simply, as in English, is if.
您可以在 Python 代码中提问,
You can ask questions in Python code along the lines of,
如果这个问题的答案是真的，那么请继续
if the answer to this question is true, then go ahead
帮我执行这个代码。
and execute this code for me.
那么让我们继续，在这里写一些这样的例子。
So let's go ahead and write some of these examples here.
我要去 VS 码。
I'm going to go over to VS Code.
让我们先创建一个程序,
And let's go ahead and create a program first,
名为 compare.py，其目标很简单
called compare.py, the goal of which is simply
编写比较值并根据这些值做出决策的代码。
to write code that compares values and makes decisions based on those values.
让我们继续输入 compare.py 的代码,
Let's go ahead and type code of compare.py,
为了创建一个全新的名为比较的文件,
in order to create a brand new file called compare,
其中我们将开始表达一些这样的逻辑。
in which we'll start to express some of this logic.
我们要比较什么？
Well, what do we want to compare?
为了便于讨论，我们来比较一下,
Suppose we want to compare, for the sake of discussion,
只有几个整数。
just a couple of integers.
但我们希望这些整数来自用户,
But we'd like those integers to come from the user,
这样我们就可以根据数字做出决定
so that we can make decisions based on numbers
我们不知道事先的价值。
we don't know the values of in advance.
我们开始吧。
Well, let's go ahead and do this.
正如我们过去所做的，让我们把它声明为一个变量，就像 x 一样。
As we've done in the past, let's declare it a variable, like x.
让我们赋值它等于 int 函数的返回值,
Let's assign it equal to the return value of the int function,
并将输入函数的返回值传递给 int 函数,
and pass to the int function the return value of the input function,
问用户一个问题，比如 x 是什么，问题
asking the user a question like, what's x, question
Mark 就像我们过去一样。
mark, as we've done in the past.
让我们对 y 再做一次，要求用户输入 y 的值。
Let's do this one more time with y, asking the user for the value of y.
同样，最终也将其转换为 int。
And, again, converting that, ultimately, to an int, as well.
这么多的故事，我们有两个变量 x 和 y,
So with this amount of the story, we have two variables, x and y,
每一个都有价值。
each of which has values.
理想情况下，我们现在应该能够比较这些值。
And ideally, we should be able to now compare these values.
假设我想根据这些变量的值来做决定。
So suppose I want to make a decision based on the values of these variables.
我会用关键词。
I'm going to use the keyword if.
我会用到一些数学符号
And I'm going to use some of those mathematical symbols
才能真正问出问题本身。
to actually ask the question itself.
这样吧，如果 x 小于 y 我们继续
So how about this, if x is less than y, then let's go ahead and just
打印出来。
print as much out.
引号 x 小于 y。
Quote, unquote x is less than y.
所以这还不是一个非常有趣的程序。
So this isn't a very interesting program yet.
根据数学，我只是在陈述显而易见的事实。
I'm literally just stating the obvious, based on the math.
但现在它允许我引入一些新的语法。
But it's allowing me to now introduce some new syntax.
具体的语法是什么？
And exactly what is the syntax?
是这个，不仅仅是“如果”这个关键词
Well, it's this-- not just the keyword if, which
我在第四行的开头添加了,
I've added here at the start of line four,
然后我问了一个问题，x 小于 y。
but then I asked my question here, x less than y.
X 是左边的一个变量，y 是右边的一个变量。
x is one variable on the left, y is one variable on the right.
当然，小于号表示的是数学问题
And, of course, the less than sign is expressing the mathematical question
是的。
I have.
我在这里强调的是技术上的
What I've highlighted here is technically
叫做布尔表达式。
called a Boolean expression.
一个以数学家布尔命名的布尔表达式,
A Boolean expression, named after a mathematician named Bool,
只是一个回答是或不是的问题，或者技术上来说,
is simply a question that has a yes or no answer, or technically,
真或假的答案。
a true or false answer.
这很好，因为如果只有两个可能的答案,
And that's nice because if there's only two possible answers,
这对我来说很容易，反过来，电脑也可以做出决定
it's very easy for me, and in turn the computer, to make a decision--
要么做，要么不做。
do this, or don't do this thing.
注意，如果你来自其他语言,
Now notice, if you come from other languages,
你可能注意到我没有输入任何括号。
you might notice that I have not typed any parentheses.
实际上，它们并不是必需的，至少在这种情况下，在 Python 中是如此,
They are not, in fact, necessary, at least in this case, in Python,
但是我在这一行的末尾打了一个冒号。
but I have typed a colon at the end of the line.
更重要的是，在下一行
And even more importantly, at the next line
我已经开始了我的线与一些压痕,
I have begun my line with some indentation,
按四次空格键或者只按一次 Tab 键,
hitting the space bar four times, or just hitting Tab once,
将自动转换为相同的。
which will automatically be converted to the same.
这种缩进告诉 Python 第5行只应该
That indentation is what tells Python that line five should only
如果第四行问题的答案事实上是正确的，则执行。
be executed if the answer to line four's question is, in fact, true.
所以如果 x 小于 y 短语会在之后打印出来。
So if x is less than y, that phrase will be printed thereafter.
我们再加几行代码。
Well, let's add a few more lines of code.
再问个问题怎么样？
How about another question?
如果 x 大于 y 那么我们继续打印它。
If x is greater than y, then let's go ahead and print that.
X 大于 y。
x is greater than y.
最后一个问题，如果 x 等于 y，等一下。
And let's do one final question, if x equals y, then-- wait a minute.
我做错了什么？
What have I done wrong here?
好眼力。
A good eye here.
我不想把 y 赋给 x。
I don't want to assign y to x.
如果 x 等于 y 是表示等式的方法，那么我们继续
If x equals equals y is how I express equality, let's go ahead
打印出 x 等于 y。
and print out x is equal to y.
现在我有三个条件,
So I now have three conditions, if you will,
一个问题要求 x 小于 y 一个问题要求 x 大于 y,
one question asking x less than y, one asking x greater than y,
一个问题是 x 等于 y。
one asking x equals equals y.
运行代码。
Let's run the code.
在我的终端窗口
Well, down here in my terminal window I'm
将运行 compare.py 的 Python 并点击 Enter。
going to run Python of compare.py and hit Enter.
X 是什么？
What's x?
我们就选一个吧。
Let's go with one.
Y 是什么？
What's y?
那就两个吧。
Let's go with two.
当然，这应该执行第一行代码
This should, of course, execute that first line of code
告诉我，确实，x 小于 y。
and tell me, indeed, that x is less than y.
正如我所料。
Exactly as I would expect there.
刚才发生了什么，用密码吗？
Well, what just happened, though, in code?
那么，让我们来看看，也许，在同样的代码视觉上,
Well, let's take a look, perhaps, at this same code visually,
特别是如果你是一个视觉学习者，这个，我敢说,
particularly if you're a more visual learner, this, I dare say,
就是刚刚发生的事。
is what just happened.
我们现在看到的是一个流程图。
So what we're looking at here is a flow chart.
这是这个程序的逻辑图。
It's a diagram of this program's logic.
从技术上讲，它展示了程序的控制流程。
And more technically, it shows the program's control flow.
也就是说，你在代码中控制的能力
That is, the ability of you, in code, to control
程序的流程，通常从上到下。
the flow of a program, generally from top to bottom.
事实上，让我继续放大这个流程图的顶部。
In fact, let me go ahead and zoom in on the top of this flow chart.
你会看到顶部有一个椭圆，字面意思是，开始。
And you'll see an oval at the very top that says, quite literally, start.
也就是说，不管是什么形状或布局
That is, irrespective of what shape or layout
这个图表就是，你自己的思维和逻辑
the diagram is, where your own thinking and logic
应该开始时，试图包装您的头脑在这个程序。
should start when trying to wrap your mind around this program.
注意，从开始到这个菱形形状有一个箭头。
Notice that there's an arrow from start to this diamond shape.
在这颗钻石里面有一个问题一个布尔表达式,
And inside of that diamond is a question, a Boolean expression,
x 小于 y。
x less than y.
这个形状意味着，基于这个问题的答案,
And this shape just means, based on the answer to that question,
向左或向右。
go left or go right.
具体来说，如果答案是真的就向左走,
Specifically, go left if the answer is true,
如果答案是错误的，就向右走。
or go right if the answer is false.
对于 x 和 y，我输入的输入分别是1和2。
Well, the inputs I typed were one and two, respectively, for x and y.
所以，当然，一比二小。
So, of course, one is less than two.
这就是为什么我的程序输出，引号，x 小于 y。
So that's why my program printed out, quote unquote, x is less than y.
但是回想一下密码。
But recall the code.
代码接着又问了两个问题。
The code then proceeded to ask two more questions.
X 大于 y 吗？
Is x greater than y?
X 等于 y 吗？
Is x equal equal to y?
流程图也描述了这些问题。
Well, the flow chart depicts those questions, too.
请注意，无论问题是否
Notice that no matter whether the question
有一个真或假的答案，箭头都收敛了下来
had an answer of true or false, the arrows both converge back down
第二个钻石形状。
to this second diamond shape here.
第二个菱形问第二个问题，x 大于 y。
And that second diamond shape asks the second question, x greater than y.
这也有一个正确或错误的答案。
That, too, has a true or false answer.
所以不管怎样，我们都要去。
So we go one way or the other.
但如果 x 是1，y 是2，那么答案是否定的。
But if x is one and y is two, then no, the answer is false.
一个并不比 y 大。
One is not greater than y.
所以从逻辑上来说，在流程图中，这次你要遵循错误的箭头。
So logically, in the flow chart, you follow the false arrow this time.
注意，沿着那个错误的箭头，这次你不会打印任何东西。
And notice, along that false arrow you don't print anything this time.
这就是为什么我们在屏幕上只看到一个打印输出。
That's why we only saw one printout on the screen.
还有第三个问题。
Now, there was still a third question.
这个流程图也捕捉到了这一点。
And this flow chart captures that, as well.
第三个菱形要求 x 等于 y。
The third diamond asks x equals equals y.
现在，在这个例子中也有一个错误的答案，因为一个，当然,
Now that, too, has a false answer in this case, because one, of course,
不等于 y。
does not equal equal y.
所以我们再次跟随第三个假分支。
And so we again follow the third false branch here.
当然，这导致我们停下来。
And that leads us, of course, to stop.
“停止”表示程序结束了。
And stop just indicates that's it for the program.
所以我认为这是正确的。
So I think that's correct.
这种特殊的流程图确实会发生
And that particular flow chart does happen
代表我写的实际代码。
to represent the actual code that I wrote.
所以是对的。
So it's correct.
它做了它该做的事。
It does what it's supposed to do.
它通过在屏幕上打印 x 小于 y 正确地回答了这个问题。
It answered the question correctly by printing on the screen x less than y.
但是，它的设计可能有什么缺陷呢？
But what is, perhaps, poorly designed about it?
让我们来做第一个区分。
Let's make this first distinction.
对于代码来说，这是不够的
It's not enough, necessarily, for the code
你写的是正确的，做你想做的。
that you write to be correct and do what you intend.
长远来看，尤其是我们的项目越来越长，越来越复杂,
Longer term, especially as our programs get longer and more sophisticated,
更复杂的是，我们也希望它们设计得很好。
more complicated, we're going to want them to be well-designed, too.
思考一下这个项目在哪些方面设计得不够好,
Thoughts on in what way this program is arguably not well designed,
即使它是正确的？
even though it's correct?
让我看看。
Let's see here.
Khalid 如果我没说错的话，你的想法呢？
Khalid, if I'm saying that right, your thoughts?
太多的如果，我认为，正在变得重复。
KHALID: Too many ifs, I think, is getting repetitive.
也许，我们可以使代码更简洁。
We can make our code more concise, maybe.
大卫. 马兰: 是的，看起来有点重复。
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, it seems a little repetitive.
我在问这个，这个，这个。
I'm asking if this, if this, if this.
然而，从逻辑上讲，我应该知道后面一些问题的答案
And yet, logically, I should know the answer to some of those later questions
只要我想出一个办法。
once I figure one out.
简而言之，如果你看这张图,
And, in short, if you look at this diagram here,
注意到不管我是向左还是向右,
notice that no matter whether I go left or I go right,
我总是问三个问题。
I'm always asking three questions.
不管怎样，所有的箭头都指向第一个，第二个,
No matter what, all of those arrows lead to the first, the second,
第三颗钻石。
and the third diamond.
所以我要问三个问题，不管是否有答案
So I'm asking three questions, no matter whether any of those answers
是真是假。
are true or false.
那我该怎么改进呢？
Well how might I go about improving this?
那么，让我提议我们引入另一个关键词
Well, let me propose that we introduce another keyword
我们的蟒蛇词汇，也就是 elif。
to our Python vocabulary, namely elif.
这个也很简洁。
And this, too, is kind of a succinct one.
这是 else 的连词，如果在英语中,
It's a conjunction of else if, in English,
这使我们能够提出一个问题，考虑到是否
which allows us to ask a question that takes into account whether or not
以前的问题有正确或错误的答案。
a previous question had a true or false answer.
我这话什么意思？
Well, what do I mean by that?
好吧，让我回到我的代码。
Well, let me go back to my code here.
让我提议，我们现在改进这个，在这里,
And let me propose that we now improve upon this, here,
通过问自己，最终，我们怎样才能问更少的问题？
by asking ourselves, ultimately, how can we ask fewer questions?
让我继续提议
And let me go ahead here and propose that
而不是问如果，如果，如果，让这些条件潜在地相互作用
instead of asking if, if, if, let's make these conditions potentially mutually
独家新闻。
exclusive.
也就是说，我们回来后不要一直回答问题
That is to say, don't keep answering questions once we get back
一个真实的答案。
a true answer.
所以我要在这里修改我的代码，如下所示。
So I'm going to change my code up here as follows.
不是问，如果，如果，我要说，如果 x 小于 y，elif x
Instead of asking if, if, if, I'm going to say, if x less than y, elif x
大于 y 的 elif x 等于 y。
greater than y, elif x equals equals y.
所以我要含蓄地，就像一个英国人,
So I'm going to implicitly, just like an English,
考虑到我只会一直问自己这些问题
take into account that I'm only going to keep asking myself these questions
如果我还没有得到真正的回应。
if I haven't yet gotten a true response.
想想这里的逻辑，英国人。
Think about the logic here, the English.
如果 x 小于 y，在第四行，打印出 x 小于 y。
If x is less than y, on line four, print out x is less than y.
如果是这样的话，逻辑上你就完了。
Well, if that's the case, you're done, logically.
因为如果英国人说如果 x 小于 y 否则如果 x 大于 y,
Because if the English is saying if x less than y, else if x greater than y,
如果第一个问题的答案是相互排斥的
those are going to be mutually exclusive if the answer to the first question
是真的。
is true.
你不必一直问那些你逻辑上已经知道的问题
You don't have to keep asking questions to which you already logically know
答案。
the answer.
现在让我继续运行这个程序。
So let me go ahead now and run this program.
我认为行为会是一样的。
And I think the behavior is going to be the same.
Python 的 compare.py，x 是什么？
Python of compare.py, what's x?
让我们做一个。
Let's do one.
Y 是什么？
What's y?
我们做两个。
Let's do two.
X 小于 y。
x is less than y.
说实话，我在运行程序的时候并没有发现有什么不同。
Now, honestly, I didn't really notice a difference when I ran the program.
说实话，现在我的 Mac 电脑，手机,
And honestly, my Mac, my PC, my phone nowadays,
如此之快，以至于这些改进
are so darn fast that these kinds of improvements
不会感觉更快，直到我们
aren't going to necessarily feel any faster until we're
编写更大、更快的程序。
writing bigger, faster programs.
但它为长期编写更好的代码奠定了基础。
But it's laying the foundation for writing better code longer term.
我刚才的进步是什么？
Now what is the improvement I've just made?
如果之前我的图像是这样的,
Well, if previously my diagram looked like this,
问题是我问了三个问题
which was problematic insofar as I was asking three questions no matter
什么，即使我已经想好要在屏幕上打印什么了。
what, even if I already figured out what I want to print on the screen.
这个程序的新版本说如果，elif，elif
This new version of the program that says if, elif, elif, might look
而不是像这样的小东西。
a little something like this instead.
现在又宽了一点。
Now it got a little wider.
那是因为我们把箭头画得更宽了。
That's just because we drew the arrows to be a bit wider here.
但是让我们关注一下到底有多少问题被问到。
But let's focus on just how many questions are getting asked.
让我像之前一样放大顶部。
Let me zoom in at the top, as before.
让我提议，我们注意到起始椭圆在顶部,
And let me propose that we note that the start oval is at the very top,
它要求我们先问一个问题。
and it's asking us to ask one question first.
X 小于 y 1小于2吗？
x less than y, is one less than two?
但是注意这里，让我放大，如果一个的确是更小的
But notice here, let me zoom out, if one is, indeed, less
两个以上，我们沿着这个长箭头向下，标记为真。
than two, we follow this longer arrow down, marked true.
我们打印出引号，引号 x 小于 y。
We print out quote, unquote x is less than y.
然后我们立即沿着下一个箭头向下到达说“停止”的图标。
But then we immediately follow this next arrow down to the icon that says stop.
这就是所谓的 if，elif，elif。
So that's what's implied by doing if, elif, elif.
如果我们马上得到一个真实的答案,
If we get back a true answer right away to that first if,
我们要打印出 x 小于 y 然后停止。
we're going to print out x is less than y and then stop.
从逻辑上讲，我们在程序的最后。
We're logically at the end of the program.
所以这张图片只是用图形表示,
So this picture is just representing, graphically,
代码到底在做什么。
what the code is actually doing.
但假设我输入了别的东西。
But suppose I typed in something else.
假设我的代码确实运行了，输入了两个 x 和一个 y。
Suppose that my code actually ran, and I typed in two for x and one for y.
也就是说，第一个问题的答案现在是错误的。
That is to say, the answer to the first question is now false.
但第二个问题的答案现在是正确的。
But the answer to the second question is now true.
因为，当然，二比一大。
Because, of course, two is greater than one.
好吧，让我们回到图表上。
Well, let's go back to the diagram.
和以前一样，我们从最上面写着开始的地方开始。
Same as before, we start at the very top where it says start.
这里的第一个问题，现在，x 小于 y，是一个错误的答案,
The very first question up here, now, x less than y, is an answer of false,
因为不，二不等于一。
because no, two is not less than one.
所以我们沿着这个箭头找到下一个问题，这颗钻石。
So we follow this arrow to the next question, this diamond.
X 大于 y 吗？
Is x greater than y?
是的，两个比一个大。
Well, yes, two is greater than one.
现在我们沿着这个左箭头，这是真的。
So now we follow this left arrow, which is true.
我们打印出引号，引号 x 大于 y，然后停止。
We print out quote, unquote x is greater than y, and then stop.
有什么进步吗？
So what's the improvement?
在第一种情况下，我们很幸运
Well, in the first case, we got lucky and we only
只要问一个问题，就搞定了。
had to ask one question and boom, we're done.
这次，我们得问两个问题，然后砰，我们就完事了。
This time, we had to ask two questions, but then boom, we're done.
只有当 x 恰好等于 y 时，我们才能找到自己，逻辑上,
Only if x happens to equal y do we actually find ourselves, logically,
一直到我的代码中的最后一个小精灵。
getting all the way down to this final elif in my code.
如图所示，只有当 x 等于 y 的时候
And pictorially, only if x is equal to y do
我们发现自己一直走到第三颗钻石,
we find ourselves going all the way down to the third diamond,
第三个问题，是否等于 y？
the third question, asking is it equal to y or not?
现在，希望这个问题的答案不是错误的。
Now, hopefully, the answer at that point is not false.
我们加入了一个错误的箭头，这样程序本身
We've included a false arrow just so that the program itself
定义明确。
is well-defined.
但从逻辑上讲，我们不应该真的到达那里,
But, logically, we shouldn't actually be getting there anyway,
因为在这种情况下，它必须小于，大于，等于。
because it's got to be less than, or greater than, or equal to in this case.
让我暂停一下，看看有没有
Well, let me pause here to see if there's
任何问题，现在，要么在这里的代码版本,
any questions, now, either on the code version thereof here,
或者在这个逻辑图上。
or on this diagramming of that very same logic.
关于这个控制流有什么问题吗？
Questions here, on this control flow?
我们不是应该在最后加一个 else 吗？
SPEAKER 1: Aren't we supposed to put an else at the end?
问得好。
DAVID MALAN: A good question.
是的，这将是我的第三个也是最后一个方法。
And yes-- so that's going to be my third and final approach.
如果你不介意的话，我们现在就开始吧。
And if you don't mind, let's pivot there right away.
确定第三个关键词，这个确实存在
Identifying a third keyword, that indeed exists
在 Python 中，这使我们能够更好地表达这种逻辑
in Python, that allows us to be even better at expressing this logic
把这个程序设计得更好。
to design this program even better.
这将解决一个特殊的问题。
And that's going to solve a particular problem.
如果我们回到这里的代码，注意
So if I take us back to our code here, notice
我之前突出显示的 elif x 等于 y。
that what I've highlighted earlier, elif x equals equals y.
问这个问题并没有错。
It's not wrong to ask that question.
事实上，如果你想特别彻底,
In fact, if you're trying to be especially thorough,
检查 x 是否小于 y 大于 y 非常有意义,
it makes perfect sense to check if x is less than y, greater than y,
或等于 y。
or equal to y.
但为什么我不需要问第三个也是最后一个问题呢？
But why don't I need to ask this third and final question?
我们不需要再问 x 是否等于 y 了，因为从逻辑上讲,
SPEAKER 2: We don't need to ask if x is equal to y any more because, logically,
如果这两个条件句的计算结果为 false,
if the two conditionals evaluate to false,
只有一个条件会求值为 true。
there is only one conditional that will evaluate to true.
也就是 x 等于 y。
And that is x is equal to y.
没错。
DAVID MALAN: Exactly.
如果我们对数学和比较都很熟悉的话
If we're all pretty comfortable with math, and comparisons
这里，当然 x 要么小于 y 要么大于 y,
here, of course x is either going to be less than y, greater than y,
或等于 y。
or equal to y.
但一旦你排除了前两种情况,
But once you rule out the first two scenarios,
逻辑上来说，x 必须等于 y。
logically, it's got to be the case that x must equal y.
如果不是这样，那就是小于或大于。
If it wasn't the case, then it's less than or greater than.
所以 Hope 建议我们用另一个关键词 else。
So Hope proposed that we use this other keyword, else.
我们怎么用这个？
And how do we use this?
就像我们用英语说的一样。
Well, exactly as we might in English.
让我回到我的代码。
Let me go back to my code here.
我没有问第三个也是最后一个问题,
And instead of bothering to ask the third and final question,
我们还是别问问题了。
let's not ask a question at all.
让我们来看看这个全面的代码，也就是说，最后一行代码说,
Let's just have this catch-all. so to speak, a final line of code that says,
否则就假设 x 等于 y。
else just assume that x is equal to y.
因此，也要打印出来。
Therefore, printing it as well.
那有什么好处呢？
So what's the upside of that?
我的代码还是一样的。
My code is still going to work exactly the same.
再说一次，我的电脑太快了
And again, my computer is so darn fast, I
甚至没有注意到它比以前工作得更快了。
don't even notice that it's working even faster than it was before.
但是我们会注意到这些事情
But we would notice these kinds of things
如果我们在这里做更多的工作，更大的项目。
if we were doing a lot more work, a lot bigger programs here.
但是让我运行 compare.py 的 Python。
But let me run Python of compare.py.
举个例子，一和二。
Let's do, for instance, one and two.
现在还有用。
Still works for that.
我们来做二加一。
Let's do two and one.
现在还有用。
Still works for that.
我们一对一。
Let's do one and one.
事实上，它现在对此很有效。
And it, indeed, now works for that.
但是在这些情况下，让我们考虑一下我们刚刚走下去的路径。
But in these cases now, let's consider the path we just went down.
以前，我们的图表，当我们有如果，elif，elif 到位,
Previously, our diagram, when we had if, elif, elif in place,
看起来有点像这个。
looked a little something like this.
注意，他们开始，我们可能会问一两个问题,
And notice, they began, we might have asked one question, or two,
或者最坏的情况，三个完整的问题。
or worst case, three whole questions.
但我们可以做得更好用别的方法，就像霍普建议的那样,
But we can do better than that, using else, as Hope proposed,
我们可以把这个图缩小到这个。
we can whittle this diagram, now, down to this.
尽管图表看起来越来越大,
And even though it looks like the diagram's getting bigger,
注意到它里面的积木越来越少。
notice that it's having fewer building blocks inside of it.
这张图中的箭头和节点都比较少。
There's fewer arrows and there's fewer nodes in this picture.
我们从头开始吧。
Let's start at the top now.
开始引导我们到第一个问题，仍然。 x 小于 y？
Start leads us to the first question, still. x less than y?
如果答案是真的，很好。
If the answer is true, great.
我们可以这么说，x 小于 y，我们可以停止。
We can say as much, x is less than y, and we can stop.
如果不是真的，如果是假的，我们可以问下一个问题。
If it's not true, if it's false, we can ask the next question.
X 大于 y，对还是错？
x is greater than y, true or false?
如果是的话，很好。
If it is, great.
我们可以打印 x 大于 y 然后停止。
We can print x is greater than y, and stop.
否则，如果 x 不大于 y，那么答案就是假的。
Else, if it's not the case that x is greater than y, the answer is false.
我们可以立即，逻辑上说 x 等于 y。
We can just immediately, logically, say x is equal to y.
我们根本不需要加上第三个问题。
We don't have to add the third question at all.
我们可以马上得出结论。
We can just immediately conclude there.
那么这意味着什么呢？
So what's the implication here?
你可以看到，通过这些图片，一个相对的下降
You can see, with these pictures, a relative decrease
在程序的复杂性中。
in the complexity of a program.
第一个很长很细，有很多很多的问题,
The first one was very long and stringy, with lots and lots of questions,
不必要的，最终。
unnecessarily, ultimately.
下一个就矮了一点。
The next one got a little shorter.
这个更短。
And this one's even shorter still.
同样，代码行数越少，发生这种情况的可能性就越小
And again, the fewer lines of code you have, the less likely
毫无疑问，你会犯任何错误。
you are, arguably, to make any mistakes.
其他人读起来就越容易。
The easier it is for other people to read.
因此，一般来说，这种可读性，这种简化,
And so, generally, this readability, this simplification,
的确是件好事。
is, indeed, a good thing.
那么，让我们继续向 Python 添加另一个功能,
Well, let's go ahead and add another piece of capability to Python,
就是这个。
and that's this one here.
就像英语一样，你可以问这个问题或者其他问题,
Just like in English, where you can ask this question or this other question,
你可以在 Python 中使用这个单词或者。
you can say the same thing in Python using literally this word or.
让我们回到我的 Python 代码。
So let me go back to my Python code here.
让我们提出几个问题
And let's propose how we might ask a couple of questions
此时此刻，也许这一次，考虑到我们可能会问不
at once this time, perhaps this time considering how we might ask not
不管它是大于还是等于,
whether or not it's greater than or equal to,
并且关心准确的答案。
and caring about the precise answer.
让我们采取一个粗略的方法。
Let's take a coarser approach here.
我们来确定 x 等于 y 还是不等于？
And let's just try to determine is x equal to y or not?
让我来删除一些代码
Well, let me go ahead and delete some of this code
改变我们的问题。
and change the question we're asking.
让我这么做，如果我关心它是否平等,
Let me do this-- well, if I care about whether it's equal or not,
我们来看看可能的情况。
let's check the possible scenarios.
如果 x 小于 y 或者 x 大于 y 我们继续
If x is less than y or x is greater than y, let's go ahead
并且打印出 x 不等于 y。
and print out x is not equal to y.
这是为什么，没有双关语吗？
Now why is that, no pun intended?
如果 x 小于 y，那么它显然不等于。
If x is less than y, well, it's obviously not equal.
如果 x 大于 y 显然不等于。
If x is greater than y, it's obviously not equal.
所以我们可以得出 x 不等于 y 的结论。
So we can conclude x is not equal to y.
所以如果我们想确保它等于,
So if we, instead, want to make sure that it is equal to,
我们可以使用 Hope 的 else，使用 print quote，unquote x 等于 y。
we can just use Hope's else, using print quote, unquote x is equal to y.
再问一次，为什么会这样？
And again, why is this?
如果 x 小于 y 或者 x 大于 y,
Well, if x is less than y, or x is greater than y,
他们显然是不平等的。
they're obviously not equal.
否则，从逻辑上讲，它们实际上必须是相等的。
Otherwise, logically, they must be equal, in fact.
那我们来看看这个。
So let's run this.
让我们继续运行 compare.py 的 Python。
Let's go ahead and run Python of compare.py.
X 是什么？
What's x?
一。
One.
Y 是什么？
What's y?
两个。
Two.
X 不等于 y。
OK, x is not equal to y.
我们再来一次，把两个代表 x，一个代表 y，x 不等于 y。
Let's do it again, put two for x, one for y. x is not equal to y.
第三次，x 是1，y 是1怎么样。
And one third time, how about x is one and y is one.
现在 x 等于 y。
x is now equal to y.
现在，如果我们想在视觉上对比一下,
Now if we want to compare that visually, too,
让我假设这幅画看起来有点像这样。
let me propose that the picture looks a little something like this.
再说一遍，这在逻辑上是完全一样的,
And again, this is the exact same thing logically,
但这只是一幅图画。
but it's a pictorial representation thereof.
第一个问题是什么？
What's the first question?
如果 x 小于 y 那我们就按照真正的箭头。
Well, if x is less than y, well, then we follow the true arrow.
我们说，引号 x 不等于 y。
And we say quote, unquote x is not equal to y.
然后我们停下来。
And then we stop.
但如果 x 不小于 y 呢？
But what if x is not less than y?
如果它比 y 大呢？
What if it's greater than y?
如果分别是2和1呢？
What if it's two and one, respectively?
那么 x 小于 y 的答案，第一个问题，是假的。
Then the answer to x less than y, first question, is false.
所以我们来这里。
So we go here.
我们问第二个问题，因为,
We ask the second question, because of the or,
这个问题是 x 大于 y 吗？
and that asks is x greater than y?
如果是这样，注意这个，我们可以重复使用这张图片的一些相同的部分,
If so, notice this, we can kind of reuse some of the same parts of this picture,
就说 x 不等于 y。
and just say x is not equal to y.
我们不需要添加不必要的箭头和广告框。
We don't need to add arrows and ad boxes unnecessarily.
我们可以重用代码行，图片的一部分，就像我们有代码行一样。
We can reuse lines of code, parts of the picture, just as we have lines of code.
然后我们停下来。
And then we stop.
最后，我们有以下几点。
Lastly, we have the following.
如果我们知道 x 不小于 y，我们就知道
If we know that x is not less than y, we know
当 x 不大于 y 时，必须是 x 等于 y 的情况。
that x is not greater than y, it must be the case that x equals y.
我们不需要问第三个问题，另一个钻石。
We don't need to ask a third question, another diamond.
我们可以马上打印，然后说停止，以及。
We can just immediately print as much, and then say stop, as well.
我能做什么？
Well, what could I do here?
我打赌我可以稍微改进一下这个代码。
I bet I could improve this code slightly.
如果我们真想吹毛求疵，我会的
And if we really want to be nitpicky, I would
认为这只是一个小小的改进,
argue that this is now really just a minor refinement,
但这是个好习惯。
but it's a good habit to get into thinking about.
我的代码还能更好吗？
Could my code be better?
我的代码可以更简单吗？
Could my code be simpler?
我可以进一步改进这个代码吗？
Could I improve this code further?
这很微妙，但我能改进一下设计吗？
It's subtle, but could I improve the design?
我能少问几个问题吗？
Could I ask fewer questions?
我可以把它收紧吗，可以这么说吗？
Could I tighten it up, so to speak?
大家怎么想？
What do folks think?
你可以问 x 等于 y。
SPEAKER 3: You can ask is x is just equal to y.
如果你输出 x 等于 y 否则 x 不等于 y。
Then if you print x is equal to y, else x is not equal to y.
完美。
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
回忆一下我们之前在可用列表中看到的其他符号之一。
Recall one of the other symbols we saw on the available list earlier.
我们可以检查不仅小于，大于，等于。
We can check not just less than, or greater than, or equal to.
我们可以问这个问题，它不等于？
We can literally ask the question is it not equal to?
为什么我们要浪费时间问它是小于还是大于？
Why are we wasting time asking if it's less than or if it's greater than?
如果你关心的只是不平等，我想我们完全可以这么做。
Well, if all you care about is is it not equal, I think we can do exactly that.
我们只问一个我们关心的简单问题。
Let's just ask the one simple question we do care about.
让我回到这里。
And so let me go back up here.
我只想说，不是这两个问题，让我们去掉 or。
And let me just say not both of these questions, let's get rid of the or.
这么说吧，如果 x 不等于 y，那就去
Let's just say if x is not equal to y, then go
X 不等于 y。
ahead and print x is not equal to y.
而且，我认为这也会起到同样的作用。
And that, too, I think is going to work exactly the same.
但现在的情况看起来有点不同了。
But the picture now looks a little bit different.
注意这是我们之前的流程图,
Notice that this was our flow chart earlier,
代表了同样的逻辑。
that represented that same logic.
有点复杂。
And there's a bit of complexity.
你得左转，你得右转,
You've got to go left, you've got to go right,
基于这几个问题的答案。
based on the answer to these couple of questions.
如果我们现在考虑这个程序的版本,
If we now take into account what this version of the program looks like,
它甚至更简单，也许是我们见过的最简单的一个。
it's even simpler, perhaps the simplest one we've seen yet.
在节目开始的时候，我们只问一个问题,
When we start off the program, we ask just one, and only one, question,
x 不等于 y 吗？
is x not equal to y?
如果是真的，我们继续输出 x 不等于 y。
And if so, true, we go ahead and print out x not equal to y.
如果答案是假的，那么，当然，它必须等于 y,
If the answer is false, then, of course, it must be equal to y,
所以我们用这个代替。
so we say that instead.
如果我们真的想要，我们可以把它倒过来。
And if we really want, we could invert this.
如果我回到我的代码，如果，不管出于什么原因,
If I go back here to my code, and if, for whatever reason,
你只是更愿意从平等或不平等的角度去思考,
you just prefer to think in terms of equal or not equal,
而不是不平等或不平等，这完全取决于你。
as opposed to not equal or equal, it's really up to you.
我们可以把它变成平等的。
We could change this to be equals equals.
但我得把我的打印报表改成相反的顺序。
But I'm going to have to change my print statements to be in the opposite order.
现在让我把这两个倒过来,
So let me go ahead, now, and reverse these two here,
然后先移动第二个，再移动第一个。
and move the second one first and the first one second.
所以现在，当我执行这段代码时，我仍然只问一个问题。
So now, when I execute this code, I'm asking still just one question.
所以还是一样好，一样简洁。
So it's still just as good, just as succinct.
但是现在这个图，看起来不像这样,
But now the diagram, instead of looking like this,
将不等式改为等式。
is going to change the not equal to equal equal.
我们只需要确保打印出来的内容是正确的。
And we just need to make sure that we print out the right thing, accordingly.
同样，这里也是，正如代码变得更紧凑一点，一点点
And again, here too, just as the code is getting a little more compact, a little
更紧凑，字符越来越少,
more compact, with fewer and fewer characters,
所以这些图表，这些流程图捕捉相对简化
so are these diagrams, these flow charts capturing the relative simplification
每一个项目也是如此。
of each of those programs, too.
让我在这里暂停一下，看看是否有任何问题，现在，对于任何问题
Let me go ahead and pause here to see if there's any questions, now, on any
这些版本的代码。
of these versions of code.
我有几个问题。
SPEAKER 4: Yeah, I have a couple of questions.
如果没有使用缩进呢？
What if indentation is not used?
马兰: 如果不使用缩进，你的程序将无法工作。
DAVID MALAN: If indentation is not used, your program will not work.
所以巨蟒和其他的有些不同
So Python is a little different from a lot
的语言，因为它强制缩进的要求。
of languages in that it enforces the indentation requirement.
你们中有些人已经编程多年了
Some of you who have been programming for years
可能不一定是正确缩进代码的最佳习惯。
might not necessarily be in the best habit of indenting your code properly.
可以说，Python 的一个特性
And one of the features, arguably, of Python
它使你缩进你的代码，否则它不仅仅是工作。
is that it makes you indent your code, or it will not just work.
我想，你还有别的问题吗？
And I think, did you have one other question?
有必要结肠吗？
SPEAKER 4: Yeah, is the colon necessary?
大卫. 马兰: 需要结肠吗？
DAVID MALAN: Is the colon necessary?
是的，结肠也是必要的。
Yes, the colon, too, is necessary.
所以对于巨蟒，你看到的就是你在这里看到的。
So with Python, what you see is what you get here.
实际上，它需要缩进，而冒号是必需的。
And, indeed, it needs to be indented and the colon is necessary.
Python 不像 C、 C + + 和 Java 那样按照约定使用,
Python does not use, in the same way by convention as C, and C++, and Java,
从花括号到内涵块。
curly braces to connote blocks.
相反，它确实依赖于这种缩进。
Instead, it relies, indeed, on this indentation.
让我提议我们在 Python 中引入另一个关键字,
Well, let me propose that we introduce one other keyword here in Python,
看看我们如何结合额外的想法。
to see exactly how we might combine additional thoughts.
这就是字面上的意思，一个词的连词,
And that's going to be literally the word and, a conjunction of one,
或者两个，或者更多的问题。
or two, or more questions that we might want to ask at once.
让我提议，在这里，我们探索这种逻辑
And let me propose, here, that we explore this kind of logic
通过另一个程序，在 VS 代码中，我现在继续
by way of another program altogether, in VS Code, whereby I'll go ahead now
然后创建一个新程序，比如，叫做 grade.py。
and create a new program, say, called grade.py.
让我们来看看一个学生应该得到什么分数,
Let's consider exactly what grade a student should get,
根据他们在考试、测验或测验中的成绩,
based on their score on an exam, or a test, or a quiz,
或者其他类似的任务。
or some other assignment like that.
我将继续运行 grade.py 代码，为自己创建一个新文件。
I'm going to go ahead and run code of grade.py, to give myself a new file.
然后我会继续，从得到用户的得分开始，再一次,
And I'm going to go ahead and start by just getting the user's score, again,
在某些作业，或测试，或类似的。
on some assignment, or test, or the like.
我要把它存储在一个叫做 score 的变量里，等于返回值
And I'm going to store it in a variable called score, equal the return
整型函数的值，它将转换用户的
value of the int function, which is going to convert whatever the user's
当提示输入这个分数时。
input is when prompted for this score.
所以，用户只需要给我一个数字，比如0或者1,
So again, the user should just oblige by giving me a number like zero, or one,
或者更高，比如97,98,99,100,
or two, or hopefully much higher than that, like 97, 98, 99, 100,
假设测试或评估满分为100分。
assuming the test or assessment is out of 100 percentage points.
现在，我该怎么给学生的分数打分呢？
Now, how could I go about assigning a grade to the student's score?
在美国，这种情况非常普遍
Well in the US, it's very commonly the case
如果你的分数在90到100之间，那就是 A。
that if you get between a 90 and 100, that's an A.
如果在80和89之间就是 B 如果是70和79就是 C,
And if it's between an 80 and a 89, it's a B. If it's 70 and 79, it's a C,
以此类推，一直到 F 应该是 E,
and so forth, all the way down to F, which should be E,
但我们会看到有一点跳跃。
but we'll see that there's a bit of a jump.
我该怎么表达呢？
So how might I express this?
我可以用条件句。
Well, I can use conditionals.
我可以问几个问题，然后打印出学生的成绩
And I can ask a few questions and then print out the student's grade
因此。
accordingly.
如果学生的分数是
So let me express it like this, if the student's score is
大于或等于90，学生的分数是
greater than or equal to 90, and the student's score is
小于或等于100，所以在这个范围内，继续
less than or equal to 100, so it's in that range, let's go ahead
打印出他们的成绩应该是 A 因为他们是90后,
and print out that their grade shall be an A. Because they're in the 90s,
以上级别范围。
above grades range.
如果分数大于等于80,
elif the score is greater than or equal to 80,
得分小于或等于，比如说，89，但是这里我有一些选择。
and the score is less than or equal to, say, 89, but here I have some options.
逻辑上，我可以用任何方式表达自己。
Logically, I can actually express myself in any number of ways.
也许只是为了更干净一点，我
And maybe just to be a little cleaner, I'm
得分低于90。
going to say a score is less than 90.
所以我使用的是 less than 而不是 less 小于等于。
So I'm using less than instead of less than or equal to.
所以我要确保他们的分数界限是正确的。
So I'm making sure that their boundaries between these grades are correct.
然后，如果学生的成绩是80分，我就给他 B。
Then, I'm going to go ahead and give the student a B if it's in the 80s.
Elif 得分大于或等于70，且得分小于80,
elif score is greater than or equal to 70, and the score is less than 80,
我要给他们打个 C。
I'm going to go ahead and give them a C.
如果得分大于或等于60，且得分小于70,
elif the score is greater than or equal to 60, and the score is less than 70,
我要给他打个 D
I'm going to go ahead and give him a D. And here's
至少在这里的一些学校是有点反常的，还有呢
where it's a little anomalous, at least in some schools here, else
我会给他们一个 F 所以我们一起跳过 E,
I'm going to go ahead and give them an F. So we're skipping E altogether,
而我们的成绩是 F。
and we're going to give an F, instead, for the grade.
这就是我要说的。
So that's the catch-all.
我想，从逻辑上来说，我是对的,
And I think, logically, I've gotten this correct,
至少从我小时候的学校来看,
at least based on where I went to school growing up,
这样就会得到 A 或者 B 或者 C 或者 D,
such that it's going to give an A, or a B, or a C, or a D,
否则它就会假设你得了个 F。
else it's going to assume that you got an F.
好吧，让我们试试这里的一些。
Well, let's try just a few of these here.
让我们运行 grade.py 的 Python。
Let's run Python of grade.py.
我的分数是，让我们开始强大，100。
My score is, let's start strong, 100.
我得了个 A 下次就没那么好了，也许是95分
I got an A. Didn't do as well the next time, maybe it's a 95--
还是 A 开始下滑，所以下次我得了89分。
still an A. Starting to slip further, so I got an 89 the next time.
现在是 B 了，假设我这周过得很糟糕,
That's now, say, a B. And let's say I really had a bad week,
现在是71分。
and it's now a 71.
现在是 C 了，或者我根本没提交，完全是 F。
That's now a C. Or I didn't even submit it at all, that's an F, altogether.
看起来有用。
So it seems to work.
这并不是一个详尽的测试，但至少
That's not really an exhaustive test, but at least
基于那里的一些采样，我的代码似乎像我期望的那样工作。
based on some sampling there, my code seems to work as I expect.
看看我们能不能把这个弄紧点。
But let's see if we can't tighten this up.
这没错。
It's not wrong.
没错。
It's correct.
事实上，根据我自己的说明,
And, indeed, according to my own specifications,
我敢说这个密码是正确的。
I dare say this code is correct.
但是我们能收紧吗？
But can we tighten it up?
我们现在还是以后能够降低错误的可能性吗？
Can we reduce the probability of bugs, now or down the line?
我们可以提高它的可读性吗？
Can we increase the readability of it?
我们能提高它的效率吗？
And can we increase the efficiency of it?
我们能让电脑少回答一些问题吗
Can we get the computer to have to answer fewer questions
结果还是一样？
and still get the same result?
看看我们能做什么。
Well, let's see what we might do.
让我换个方式来证明我们可以
Let me just switch things up, if only to demonstrate that we can
以不同的方式使用这些符号。
use these symbols in different ways.
我可以这样说，如果分数大于或等于90。
I could say, as I've done, if score is greater than or equal to 90.
但我真的可以做到，我可以把它翻过来。
But I can actually do this, I can flip it around.
不是说大于或等于,
Instead of saying greater than or equal to,
假设90小于或等于得分。
let's say 90 is less than or equal to score.
这里，假设80小于等于得分。
And here, let's say if 80 is less than or equal to score.
这里，70小于或等于得分。
And here, 70 is less than or equal to score.
最后，60小于等于得分。
And then, lastly, 60 is less than or equal to score.
所以从逻辑上讲，这是一回事。
So it's the same thing, logically.
我只是把东西换一下，就像你在纸笔上做的那样
I'm just switching things around, just like you could do on paper pencil
如果你真的想的话。
if you really wanted.
但现在注意这个小把戏。
But now notice this trick.
对于那些用 C 或者 C + + 编程的人来说这是不可能的,
And this is not possible, for those of you who have programmed in C, or C++,
或者 Java 或者其他语言。
or Java, or other languages.
注意，我可以把这些范围结合起来。
Notice what I can do here is actually combine these ranges.
注意我在问两个问题，两个布尔表达式。
Notice that I'm asking two questions, two Boolean expressions.
90是否小于或等于得分，得分是否小于或等于100？
Is 90 less than or equal to score, and is score less than or equal to 100?
巨蟒允许你像这样嵌入这些东西,
Well, Python allows you to nest these things like this,
把他们锁在一起。
and chain them together.
就像你在现实生活中用纸笔写字一样,
And just like you would on paper pencil in the real world,
你可以用 Python 编码，这样做，这样会更干净一点。
you can encode in Python, do this, which is just a little cleaner.
密码有点紧了。
It's tightening up the code a little bit.
敲键盘的次数更少。
It's fewer keystrokes.
打字更快。
It's faster to type.
向前看更容易理解。
It's easier to read, moving forward.
所以这也可以说是更好的。
So that's arguably better, as well.
这是一个进步。
So that's one improvement.
在这种情况下，主要是审美上的。
It's largely aesthetic, in this case.
它仍然在问同样多的问题,
It's still asking the same number of questions,
但它还是做得更简洁一些。
but it's doing it a little more succinctly still.
接下来我还能做什么？
Well, what more could I do here next?
你知道吗？
Well, you know what?
每次我决定分数的时候，我都不知道
Each time I'm deciding these grades, I don't
我想我得问两个问题。
think I have to ask two questions.
我不用问，是大于90还是小于100？
I don't have to ask, is it greater than 90 and less than 100?
是大于80还是小于90？
Is it greater than 80 and less than 90?
如果我重新思考我的逻辑，也许我能做得更好。
If I rethink my logic, I can maybe do this better still.
让我提议我们进一步简化这个过程，然后就这样做。
Let me propose that we simplify this further, and just do this.
如果我们知道输入目前在0和100之间,
If we know that input, for the moment, is going to be within 0 and 100,
我们可以做一些假设。
we can make some assumptions.
我们可以说，如果分数大于或等于90,
We could say something like, if the score is greater than or equal to 90,
如果分数大于或等于80，学生会得到一个 A. elif,
well, the student gets an A. elif the score is greater than or equal to 80,
学生得到一个 B。 elif 分数大于或等于70,
the student gets a B. elif score is greater than or equal to 70,
如果分数大于或等于60，他们得到一个 C,
they get a C. elif the score is greater than or equal to 60,
他们得了 D 否则就得了 F 我都干了些什么？
they get a D, else they get an F. So what have I done here?
与其每次问两个问题,
Well, instead of asking two questions every time,
检查该范围的下界和上界,
checking the lower bounds and the upper bound of that range,
我更聪明地问你分数是否大于90,
I'm being a little more clever here by asking if the score is greater than 90,
他们显然得了 A 或者更好的成绩。
well, they've obviously gotten an A or better.
如果你的分数大于80，那么，你也是
If your score is greater than 80, well, you either
如果它真的很强，就应该得 A 如果它刚好在80以上，就应该得 B。
deserve an A if it's really strong, or a B if it's just above 80.
但是因为精灵逻辑，我们已经检查过了
But because of the elif logic, we've already checked
这个学生的分数大于90吗？
is the student's score greater than 90?
如果不是，那么我们就会问这个问题，是不是大于80？
And if it's not, then we're asking the question, well, is it greater than 80?
所以你隐含地知道它在80到89之间,
So you implicitly know it's somewhere in the 80 to 89 range,
否则你知道它在70到79之间，否则它就在下一个范围内
else you know it's in the 70 to 79 range, else it's in the next range
放下。
down.
因此，这是一个小的优化，使我们能够提出更少的问题。
So it's a minor optimization that allows us to ask fewer questions.
但是同样的，它使得代码，可以说，更具可读性,
But again, it's making the code, arguably, a little more readable,
当然更简洁，然后，希望，更可维护
certainly more succinct, an then, hopefully, more maintainable
长远来看。
longer term.
那么，关于这些类型的变化,
Any questions, then, on these types of changes,
这种逻辑与我们的代码？
and this type of logic with our code?
如果我们根本不用小精灵呢？
SPEAKER 4: What if we don't use elif at all?
如果我们在 if 中编写代码呢？
What if we write the code in if?
大卫. 马兰: 是的，这是个好问题,
DAVID MALAN: Yeah, so that's a good question,
因为它实际上会在这里产生意想不到的效果。
because it's actually going to have an unintended effect here.
让我暂时去掉 F
Let me get rid of the F temporarily, and just
把注意力集中在 A 到 D 如果我们回到
focus on A through D. If we revert to where
我们用条件句开始今天的故事,
we began today's story, with conditionals, saying if,
如果，如果，如果，现在我们聪明地使用更广泛的笔触
if, if, if, now our cleverness here of using broader strokes
并且不使用上限和下限范围
and not using an upper and lower bound ranges
都会成为负面影响。
is going to come back to be a downside.
让我继续运行 grade.py 的 Python。
Let me go ahead and run Python of grade.py.
假设我的分数是95。
And suppose my score is 95.
我太激动了。
I am so darn excited.
我想拿 A 但不行。
I want my A, but nope.
我只得了 A B C 和 D 所以从逻辑上来说，这就是破碎的东西。
I just got an A, a B, a C, and a D. So logically, that's broken things.
因为如果你不让这些条件互相排斥,
Because if you don't make these conditions mutually exclusive,
所有这些问题都会被问到，因此也会得到答案。
every one of those questions is going to get asked, and therefore answered.
即使你的成绩超过了90分
And even if your grade is above a 90, it's
逻辑上也是80以上70以上60以上,
also, logically, above an 80, above a 70, above a 60,
如果我把它放在那里，我也会不及格，得个 F。
and if I'd kept it in there, I would have failed, as well, with an F.
问得好。
Really good question.
关于这种逻辑形式，还有其他问题吗？
Other questions here, on this form of logic?
还有什么更好的方法
SPEAKER 5: Would there be any better way to clean up
即使只是这个简单的声明，就像我们以前做的那样,
even just this simple statement, like we had before,
你和小精灵之间的那个？
the previous one that you had with the elif?
大卫. 马兰: 我喜欢你进一步简化事情的热情。
DAVID MALAN: I like your enthusiasm for simplifying things further.
我要大胆猜测一下这已经是最好的结果了,
I'm going to go out on a limb here and say this is about as good as it gets,
至少只使用条件语句。
at least using only conditional statements.
如果我走神的话，我可以想出一个更聪明的办法
I can, if my mind wanders, think of a slightly more clever way
做这个，也许用一个叫做循环的东西,
to do this, maybe with something called a loop,
或者其他编程构造。
or another programming construct.
我们的字典里还没有这个词。
We don't have that yet in our vocabulary.
但是，是的，绝对还有其他方法可以做到。
But yes, there's absolutely other ways to do it.
但我认为如果我们想限制自己的话，现在还不是时候
But I think not yet if we want to restrict ourselves
比如 if，and，and else，elif，and，and 等等。
to just words like if, and or, and else, and elif, and and, and the like.
那么，让我提议我们现在转向使用另一种方法
Well, let me propose that we pivot now to use another approach here
使用了另一个符号，直到现在,
that uses one other symbol that, up until now,
我们还没有机会利用。
we've not really had occasion to use.
让我提议我们实现一个程序，我们称之为奇偶校验。
Let me propose that we implement a program that we'll call parity.
在数学中，奇偶性可以指一个数是偶数还是奇数。
In mathematics, parity can refer to whether a number is even or odd.
这是个有趣的问题。
And that's kind of an interesting question.
结果证明它在其他应用中也很有用,
And it turns out it can be useful in other applications,
同样，只要问一个给定的数字是偶数还是奇数,
too, to just ask the question is a given number even or odd,
也许是用户输入的？
maybe that the user typed in?
让我继续写一个新程序
And let me go ahead and write a new program
在我的终端中通过代码 parity.py 命名为 parity.py。
called parity.py, via code parity.py in my terminal.
我建议我们利用这个机会
And let me propose that we use this as an opportunity
介绍最后一个算术符号,
to introduce the last of those arithmetic symbols,
至少大部分我们都很熟悉加减法,
at least most of which we're familiar with, addition, subtraction,
乘法，除法。
multiplication, division.
但是这个名单之前有过，最后一个，百分比符号。
But there's been on this list before, this last one here, a percent sign.
这并不意味着百分比,
And it doesn't mean percentage in this case,
当在 Python 编程中用作运算符时。
when used as an operator in programming in Python.
相反，它表示所谓的模运算符,
Rather, it represents the so-called modulo operator,
同余关系。
for modular arithmetic.
或者，至少在我们的例子中，我们要用它来计算
Or, at least in our case, we're going to use it to calculate the remainder when
把一个数除以另一个数。
dividing one number by another.
我这话什么意思？
Well, what do I mean by that?
如果你取1除以3这样的数,
Well, if you take a number like one divided by three,
三个不会干净利落地进入一个。
three does not go into one cleanly.
所以你得到了1的余数。
So you have a remainder of one.
二除以三等于二的余数。
Two divided by three has a remainder of two.
三除以三等于零的余数，因为它除得很清楚。
Three divided by three has a remainder of zero, because it divides cleanly.
4除以3等于1的余数因为你可以把它除以一次,
Four divided by three has a remainder of one, because you can divide it in once,
然后剩下一个，所以剩下一个。
but then that leaves one, so it has a remainder of one.
最后是5除以3
And then lastly, something like five divided by three
当然还有两个余数。
has a remainder, of course, of two.
这就是我们所说的余数，剩下多少
So that's all we mean by remainder, how much is left over
在把一个数除以另一个数之后。
after dividing one number by another.
如果我现在回到我的代码，并考虑如何实现
Well, if I go back now to my code, and I consider how I might implement
问题是这个数字是偶数还是奇数？
the question is this number even or odd?
让我们考虑一下如何实现这一点,
Let's consider how we might implement that,
因为我们如何
since it's perhaps not necessarily obvious how we
可以使用这个额外的构件。
can use this additional building block.
但事实证明，长期来看，这是非常有用的。
But it turns out it's going to be very useful longer term.
首先我们从用户那里得到一个变量 x 中的数字。
Well, let's first just get a number from the user in a variable called x.
我要把它设置为转换为 int
And I'm going to set that equal to the conversion to int
不管用户输入什么，在问他们什么是 x 之后，问号。
of whatever the user inputs, after asking them what's x, question mark.
我们以前也这么做过很多次。
And we've done that before, many times.
现在如何确定 x 是偶数还是奇数？
How do I now determine if x is even or odd?
事实证明，如果我能接触到一个程序操作员，它会告诉我
Well, it turns out, if I have access to a programmatic operator that tells me
剩下的，我想我可以做到。
the remainder, I think I can do this.
事实上，让我问问大家。
In fact, let me just ask the group.
这也许只是小学数学,
And this is just from grade school math, perhaps,
数字是偶数意味着什么？
what does it mean for a number to be even, ?
说清楚，像0,2,4,6,8,10,12,14,16这样的数字,
To be clear, a number like 0, 2, 4, 6, 8, 10, 12, 14, 16,
这些都是偶数。
those are all even numbers.
但这到底意味着什么？
But what does that really mean?
埃琳娜，如果我没说错的话？
Elena, if I'm saying that right?
偶数可以精确地除以2。
ELENA: Even numbers that can divide it exactly by two.
例如，2、4、6、8和10，还有——
For example, 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10, and--
完美。
DAVID MALAN: Perfect.
我们可以一整天都这样，真的,
And we could go on all day long, literally,
因为偶数的数量是无限的。
since there's an infinite number of those even numbers.
但你用问题的形式表达出来，这很好
But it's nice that you formulated it in terms of a question
我们可以很清楚地问。
that we can ask very clearly.
这个数字是被2整除的吗？
Is this number cleanly divided by two?
也就是说，我们能不能把它除以二，没有余数，一个零的余数？
That is, can we divide it by two with no remainder, a remainder of zero?
很好，因为如果我们有这个运算符，这个百分号，那个
Well, that's perfect, because if we have this operator, this percent sign, that
让我们可以回答，余数是多少，我们大概可以检查
allows us to answer just that, what is the remainder, we can presumably check
余数是0还是1？
is the remainder zero, or is it one?
我们什么都没剩下，还是只剩下一个？
Do we have nothing left over, or do we have one left over?
好吧，我们来问问。
Well, let's ask that.
如果 x 除以2的余数为零，就像 Elena 提出的那样，让我们继续
If x divided by two has a remainder of zero, as Elena proposes, let's go ahead
然后打印出引号，甚至引号。
and print out something like quote, unquote even.
对使用者也这么说。
And just say as much to the user.
否则，我认为我们可以假设，如果一个数字不是偶数,
else, I think we can assume that if a number's not even,
如果它确实是一个整数，那么它就是奇数。
it's going to be odd, if it's, indeed, an integer.
所以我要打印出引号，而不是引号单数。
So I'm going to go ahead and print out quote, unquote odd instead.
现在让我们继续，在我的提示符中运行 parity.py 的 Python。
And let's go ahead and now run Python of parity.py in my prompt.
X 是什么？
What's x?
我们从两个开始。
Let's start with two.
事实上，两个人甚至。
Two is, in fact, even.
我们从四开始。
Let's start with four.
事实上，是四个。
Four is, in fact, even.
我们来玩三个人的游戏吧。
Let's get interesting with three.
三现在是奇数。
Three is now odd.
我想我们可以一整天都这样做，希望能够回来，真的,
And I think we could do that all day long and hopefully get back, indeed,
就是这个答案。
exactly that answer.
但我们还能做什么呢？
But what more could we do here?
我们怎样才能改进这一点呢？
How could we improve upon this?
回想一下，我们有能力发明我们自己的功能。
Well, recall that we have the ability to invent our own functions.
我提议，为了讨论起见,
And let me just propose, for the sake of discussion,
我们最终会发现
that we're going to eventually find that it's
有助于判断一个数字是偶数还是奇数。
useful to be able to determine if a number is even or odd.
所以我们希望内置这个功能。
And so we'd like to have that functionality built-in.
而且我觉得 Python 没有功能告诉我这些。
And I don't think Python has a function for telling me just that.
但是我可以用这样的代码发明它。
But I can invent it using code like just this.
让我们回到我之前的版本。
So let me go into my earlier version here.
让我提议我们这么做。
And let me propose that we do this.
让我继续编写一个 main 函数。
Let me go ahead and write a main function.
我将重新养成定义要表示的主函数的习惯
I'm going to get back into that habit of defining a main function to represent
我计划的主要部分。
the main part of my program.
我要重蹈覆辙。
And I'm going to do what I did before.
我要从用户输入中得到一个整数,
I'm going to get an integer from the user's input,
问他们 X 是什么，问号。
asking them what's x, question mark.
然后我会问这个问题。
And then I'm going to ask this question.
目前，我还是天真地认为
For the moment, I'm going to naively assume
函数已经存在，但是
that the function already exists, but that's
一种有用的解决问题的技巧。
a useful problem-solving technique.
即使我还不知道接下来要说什么,
Even if I have no idea yet where I'm going with this,
我将如何发明一个函数来确定一个数字是否是偶数,
how I'm going to invent a function that determines if a number is even,
我假设有一个叫做“ is even”的函数
I'm just going to assume that there's a function called "is even,"
我会盲目地称之为，就像这样。
and I'm going to call it, blindly, like this.
如果是偶数，传入 x，然后继续打印引号，取消引号偶数。
If is even, passing in x, then go ahead and print quote, unquote even.
所以如果这个神奇的函数“ is even”返回 true 作为它的返回值
So if this magical function called "is even" returns true, as its return value
我要打印出它是偶数。
I am going to print out that it's even.
否则，否则，我会假设，当然，这是奇怪的。
Else, otherwise, I'm going to assume that it's, of course, odd.
现在这个程序的一个问题就算我在这里调用 main,
Now the one problem with this program, even if I call main over here,
就是根本不存在。
is that is even does not exist.
如果我现在运行这个程序，它就会中断。
And this program would break if I ran it right now.
不过没关系。
But that's OK.
我有能力，回忆，发明我自己的功能。
I have the ability, recall, to invent my own function.
让我用 def 定义一个名为“ is even”的函数
So let me define, with def, a function called "is even."
我想让这个函数接受一个参数。
I want this function to take an argument.
我把它叫做 n，只是一个数字，通常来说。
And I'm going to call it n, just a number, generically.
我可以叫它 X。
I could call it x.
但是，我不想把自己搞糊涂，弄不清楚哪个 x 是哪个。
But again, I don't want to confuse myself as to which x is which.
所以我要给它起个不同的名字，没关系。
So I'm going to give it a different name, and that's fine.
我把它叫做，更一般地说，n 代表数字。
I'm just going to call it, more generically, n for number.
然后我要做这个。
And then I'm going to do this.
如果 N% 2等于0就像之前一样,
I'm going to say if N % two equals equals zero, just like before, then,
这就是魔术，你，程序员,
and here's the magic, you, the programmer,
实际上可以返回所谓的布尔值。
can actually return what are called Boolean values.
我们已经在 Python 中看到 Python 有 Stis 或者 string 整型或者整型,
We've seen in Python that Python has stirs or strings, ints or integers,
浮点值或浮点值，所有这些
floats or floating point values, all of which
是 Python 中不同类型的数据。
are different types of data in Python.
Python 还有第四种数据类型 bool，用于布尔值。
Python also has a fourth data type called bool for a Boolean value.
虽然这只是增加了我们的名单，关于布尔的好处
And even though this is just adding to our list, the nice thing about bools
它们只能是真或假。
is that they can only be true or false.
Int 可以是任意数量的无限可能的值。
An int can be any number of an infinite possible values.
愚蠢只能是真或假。
A bool can only be true or false.
如果你写自己的话，它必须是大写的 T 和大写的 F。
And it must be capital T and capital F if you're writing itself.
所以如果我现在回到我的代码，我考虑
So if I go back now to my code, and I consider
正是我想回到这里的东西。
exactly what I want to return here.
如果 n% 2等于0,
Well, if n % two equals equals zero, that is,
如果 n 除以2的余数是0我认为它是偶数,
if n divided by two has a remainder of zero, well, I think it's even,
埃琳娜，你的定义。
to, Elena, your definition.
那么让我们返回真，大写的 T，如果它没有零的余项,
So let's return true, capital T. else, if it doesn't have a remainder of zero,
我很确定，从数学上来说，它必须有1的余项。
I'm pretty sure, mathematically, it's got to have a remainder of one.
但这不重要。
But it doesn't matter.
我知道它不是偶数，所以我要返回 false。
I know it's not even, so I'm going to return false.
我们返回 false，而不是大写 F，现在我们已经定义了两个主要的
And we return false, instead capital F. And now that we've defined both main
而且是偶数，我在底部调用 main，我想我是对的。
and is even, and I'm calling main at the bottom, I think I've got this right.
Python 的 parity. py，Enter。
Python of parity.py, Enter.
X 是什么？
What's x?
我们试试简单的，比如两个。
Let's try something simple, like two.
现在扯平了。
And it's even.
我们再来一次。
Let's do it again.
X 是什么？
What's x?
四个怎么样？
How about four?
甚至。
Even.
再问一次，X 是什么？
Once more, what's x?
三个怎么样？
How about three?
这很奇怪。
And it's odd.
我到底做了什么？
Now, what have I done here?
我只是想说，如果我想创建自己的函数“ is”
I've just made the point that if I want to create my own function called "is
甚至,”为我回答了这个问题,
even," that answers this question for me,
我现在可以在这个程序中使用，也许还有未来的程序
that I can now use, in this program, and heck, maybe future programs
我现在有一个没人给我的函数,
that I write, I now have a function that no one gave me,
我给自己，我可以使用和再利用。
I gave myself, that I can use and reuse.
我甚至可以和其他人分享。
And I can even, perhaps, share it with others.
我现在在第三行使用这个函数来做决定。
I'm using that function now on line three, just to make a decision.
我在上面用了条件句。
I'm using a conditional up there.
我的布尔表达式是对还是错,
And my Boolean expression, something that's true or false,
不是很明确的比如 x 小于 y,
is going to be not something explicit, like x less than y,
或者 y 大于 x 之类的。
or y greater than x, or the like.
这将是一个函数调用。
It's going to be a function call.
我使用一个函数作为布尔表达式。
I'm using a function as my Boolean expression.
但是没关系，因为我知道，因为是我写的,
But that's OK because I know, because I wrote it,
函数“ is even”返回 true 或者 false。
that that function "is even" returns true or it returns false.
这就是我做决定所需要的条件
And that's all I need in a conditional to make a decision
打印偶数或奇数。
to print even or print odd.
所以让我在这里暂停一下，看看现在是否有任何问题，关于我已经
So let me pause here to see if there's any questions now on how I've
实现的“是偶数”，使用这个 bool。
implemented "is even," using this bool.
你好，大卫。
SPEAKER 6: Hello, hi David.
首先，感谢你们今天给我们上了这么棒的课
First of all, thank you for this wonderful class the day
在昨天和今天之前，先生。
before yesterday and today, sir.
我只有一个基于 Java 背景的查询。
I have just one query, based on the background of Java.
在这里，当我们传递论点的时候,
There, when we used to pass the argument,
我们也可以传递变量的地址。
we can also pass the address of the variables.
那么 Python 中有类似的概念吗？
So is there any sort of this concept in Python?
大卫. 马兰: 简短的回答，不。
DAVID MALAN: Short answer, no.
那些不熟悉 Java 或其他语言，或 C，或 C + + ,
Those who are unfamiliar with Java or other languages, or C, or C++,
通常有方法在不同的机制中传递值,
there's generally ways to pass values in different mechanisms that allow you,
或者拒绝你，去改变他们。
or disallow you, to change them.
在巨蟒里，没有。
In Python, no.
我们将要看到的一切实际上都是一个物体。
Everything we're going to see is actually, in fact, an object.
不过接下来还有更多。
But more on that down the line.
还有一个问题，关于这些布尔和这些
How about time for one more question here on these bools and these
“是偶数”
"is evens."
我有一个关于定义函数的问题,
SPEAKER 7: So I actually had a question about defining a function,
如果可以的话。
if that's OK.
当然。
DAVID MALAN: Sure.
如果你在你的代码里定义一个，就像你自己编的一样,
SPEAKER 7: So if you define one, within your code, like you made it up,
你是否可以使用点运算符，就像我们使用名字点条一样,
are you allowed to use the dot operator like we did name dot strip,
然后像那样使用它？
and use it like that?
问得好。
DAVID MALAN: Good question.
如果您已经创建了自己的函数，那么您可以
If you've created your own function, can you
使用其他函数，如点条、点标题或点大写,
use other functions, like dot strip, or dot title, or dot capitalize,
我们以前见过的？
that we've seen in the past?
你可以把它们用在琴弦上。
You can use those on strings.
这些函数都带有字符串。
Those functions come with strings.
你不能把它们用在你自己的功能上,
You can't necessarily use them on your own functions,
除非你的函数返回一个字符串。
unless your function returns a string, for the examples you gave.
我是来还债的。
I'm returning a bool.
Bools 没有左右空白的概念。
Bools have no notion of white space to the left or the right.
你不能给脱衣舞娘打电话，也不能给资本公司打电话。
You can't call strip, you can't call capitalize.
但如果你写一个不同的函数
But if you were writing a different function
返回一个字符串。
that returns a string, absolutely.
你也可以使用这些功能。
You could use those functions, as well.
如果可以的话，让我们把注意力转回到这个例子上
Well, let me turn our attention, if I may, back to this example
在这里，考虑到，正如我们现在经常做的,
here, and consider, as we now frequently do,
我们可以改进这个代码的设计吗？
can we improve on the design of this code?
我可以把这个程序做得更好吗？
Can I make this particular program better?
我可以。
And I can.
有几种方法。
There's a couple of ways here.
我会给你们看一些现在通常被称为 Python 的东西。
And I'll show you something that's now generally known as something Pythonic.
实际上在巨蟒的世界里有一个艺术术语,
There's actually this term of art, in the Python world,
如果只是用 Python 做事情的方式，那么它就是 Python 的。
where something is Pythonic if it's just the way you do things in Python.
也就是说，我们已经看到
Which is to say, we've seen already there's
有那么多不同的方法来解决某些问题。
so many different ways to solve certain problems.
在 Python 程序员社区中,
And in the Python community of programmers,
总有一些方法比其他方法更容易被人笑到最后。
there tend to be some ways that are smiled upon more than others.
它们往往涉及到可能只有 Python 才有的特性,
And they tend to relate to features that maybe only Python has,
而不是其他语言。
but not other languages.
这里有一些你可能没有在 Java 这样的语言中看到过的语法,
And here's some syntax that you might not have seen in languages like Java,
或者 C，或者 C + + ，如果你以前编过程序的话。
or C, or C++ if you've programmed before.
如果你从来没有编写过程序，这也将是全新的。
And if you've never programmed before, this too is going to be new.
与其问这样的问题不如在 Python 中使用四行代码,
Instead of asking a question like this, if else using four lines, in Python,
如果你愿意的话，你可以把它折叠成一条更优雅的线条。
you can actually collapse this into just one more elegant line, if you will.
不是问 n 除以2的余数是否为零,
Instead of asking if n divided by two has a remainder of zero,
返回 true，否则返回 false。
return true, else return false.
让我删除所有这些，如果 n 除以2返回 true
Let me delete all of that and just say this, return true if n divided by two
有一个零的余数，否则返回 false。
has a remainder of zero, else return false.
那些有编程经验的人
Now those of you who do have prior programming experience
可能会觉得这样很酷。
might actually think this is kind of cool.
你可以把同样的想法，从四行浓缩成一行。
You can condense, from four lines into one line, that very same thought.
Python 之所以流行的原因之一就是它确实流行
And one of the reasons why Python is popular is that it does
读起来有点像英语。
tend to read rather like English.
它不像大多数英语或大多数人类语言那样友好。
It's not quite as user-friendly as most English, or most human languages.
但是请注意，现在，这行确实说明了你的意思。
But notice, now, the line does rather say what you mean.
如果 n 除以2的余数为零，则返回 true，否则返回 false。
Return true if n divided by two has a remainder of zero, else false.
用英语来说，逻辑上来说，这非常接近你可能会说的话,
That's pretty darn close to something you might say, logically, in English,
不管是偶数还是奇数，或者其他任何东西。
be it about even and odd or really anything else.
所以这个程序的工作原理是一样的。
So that program is going to work exactly the same.
Python 的 parity.py，让我输入两个。
Python of parity.py, let me type in two.
还是扯平了。
It's still even.
让我输入三个。
Let me type in three.
还是很奇怪。
It's still odd.
但我可以进一步完善。
But I can refine this even further.
同样，与这种不只是编写正确代码的想法一致,
And again, consistent with this idea of not just writing correct code,
但编写越来越好的代码，但仍然保持可读性,
but writing better and better code, but still keeping it readable,
我可以做一个比这个更好的。
I can do one even better than this.
注意这里的值是我的布尔表达式。
Notice this value here is my Boolean expression.
它的值是真还是假。
And it is going to evaluate to true or false.
N 除以2的余数是否为零？
Is n divided by two having a remainder of zero or not?
根据定义，这是一个布尔表达式。
That is, by definition, a Boolean expression.
它有一个是/否的答案，一个真/假的答案。
It has a yes/no answer, a true/false answer.
如果你的布尔表达式本身有一个真或假的答案,
Well, if your Boolean expression itself has a true or false answer,
你一开始为什么要问这个问题？
why are you asking a question in the first place?
为什么问如果？
Why ask if?
还能说什么？
Why say else?
只需返回您自己的布尔表达式的值。
Just return the value of your own Boolean expression.
也许是最严谨的版本，最简洁，仍然可读,
And perhaps the tightest version, the most succinct, and still readable,
这段代码的版本就是删除这一整行，Python
version of this code would be to delete this whole line, Pythonic
尽管如此，只要返回 n 模2等于0。
though it is, and just return n modulo two equals equals zero.
如果有帮助的话，让我暂时加上括号,
If it helps, let me add parentheses temporarily,
因为括号里的事情会先发生。
because what's going to happen in parentheses will happen first.
N 除以2有或没有零的余数。
n divided by two either does or does not have a remainder of zero.
如果真是这样，那答案就是真的。
If it does, the answer is true.
如果答案是否定的，那么答案就是错误的。
If it doesn't, the answer is false.
如果你愿意的话，就把问题还给我。
So just return the question, if you will.
不需要显式地用 if 和 else 包装它。
You don't need to wrap it, explicitly, with an if and an else.
事实上，由于行动的顺序,
And in fact, because of order of operations,
你甚至不需要括号。
you don't even need the parentheses.
所以现在这可能是实现这个想法的最优雅的方式。
So now this is perhaps the most elegant way to implement this same idea.
现在，哪个更好？
Now, which is better?
这真是太棒了。
This is pretty darn good.
这很难挑剔，因为它是如此的简洁。
And it's hard to take fault with this because it's so very succinct.
但这完全没问题，而且正确无误,
But it's perfectly OK, and just as correct,
有一个如果，然后一个别的。
to have an if and then an else.
虽然总共可能有四行，如果有帮助的话
Even though it might be four total lines, if that helps
你可以更清楚地思考你的代码，这会有所帮助
you think about your code more clearly, and it helps
其他人也会对此进行推理。
other people reason about it, as well.
这里还有另一种语法
So it turns out there's another syntax that you
可以用来实现条件的相同思想,
can use to implement the same idea of a conditional,
你可以根据布尔函数的答案选择性地做某件事
whereby you do something optionally, based on the answer to some Boolean
表情。
expression.
在最新版本的 Python 中，您现在可以使用的关键字是,
And the keyword that you can now use, in recent versions of Python,
叫做，火柴。
is called this-- match.
匹配是一种机制，如果你以前编写过程序，在精神上是相似的
Match is a mechanism that, if you've programmed before, is similar in spirit
在其他语言中叫做开关。
to something called switch in other languages.
例如，让我在这里结束 parity.py，然后让我继续
For instance, let me go ahead here and close out parity.py And let me go ahead
并创建一个名为 house.py 的新文件。
and create a new file called house.py.
还有 House 我想我们要去的地方
And in house.py, I think what we're going
要做的就是尝试实现一个程序，提示用户输入他们的名字,
to do is try to implement a program that prompts the user for their name,
然后输出他们所知道的房子
and then just outputs what house they're known
进入哈利波特的世界。
to be in in the world of Harry Potter.
例如，让我继续做这个。
So for instance, let me go ahead and do this.
让我给自己一个名为 name 的变量，设置它等于 return
Let me give myself a variable called name, set it equal to the return
输入函数的值。
value of the input function.
我会说，你叫什么名字，问号。
And I'll say something like, what's your name, question mark.
在那之后，我会用
And then after that, I'm just going to use
一个传统的 if，elif，else 结构来决定这个人在哪个房子里。
a traditional if, elif, else construct to decide what house this person is in.
如果名字等于哈利，比如哈利波特,
So let me say if name equals equals, say Harry, as in Harry Potter, well,
我们把哈利的房子打印出来，也就是格兰芬多
let's go ahead and print out Harry's house, which is Gryffindor
在哈利波特的世界里。
in the world of Harry Potter.
那就叫小精灵吧，赫敏
elif the name is, instead, Hermione, then
打印出格兰芬多的原话,
go ahead and print out also quote, unquote Gryffindor,
因为她也在同一个屋檐下。
as she's in the same house, too.
Elif 名字等于 Ron 我们继续
elif name equals equals Ron, let's go ahead
打印出格兰芬多的名言。
and similarly print out Gryffindor quote, unquote.
现在让我们把这个变得更有趣一点。
And let's make this a little more interesting now.
小精灵的名字等于引号，那德拉科呢？
elif name equals quote, unquote how about Draco?
德拉科 · 马尔福，在书里我们打印出引文,
Draco Malfoy, in the books-- let's go ahead and print out quote,
引用斯莱特林的话。
unquote Slytherin.
以防有人输入了别人的名字,
And just in case someone else's name gets inputted,
现在，假设我们不认识他们,
for now, let's just suppose that we don't recognize them,
默认情况下，输出引号,
and say, by default, else print out quote,
问号，只是为了表达
unquote who, question mark, just to convey
我们对这个名字并没有固定的反应。
that we don't actually have a hard-coded response to that particular name.
现在，让我继续前进，并以 house.py 和 Enter 的 Python 方式运行它。
Let me go ahead, now, and run this as Python of house.py, Enter.
然后我会继续输入像哈利这样的东西。
And I'll go ahead and type in something like Harry.
瞧，我们看到哈利确实在格兰芬多。
And voila, we see that Harry is, indeed, in Gryffindor.
让我们再运行一次，house.py 的 Python。
Let's run it one more time, Python of house.py.
这次我们输入 Draco。
Let's type in Draco this time.
斯莱特林。
Slytherin.
现在，让我们输入一个无法识别的名称。
And now, let's type in an unrecognized name.
让我们继续并重新运行 house.py 的 Python。
Let's go ahead and rerun Python of house.py.
然后输入博多河回车。
And let's go ahead and type in Padma, Enter.
还有谁？
And who?
因为在这种情况下我们没有用 elif 条件进行硬编码,
Because we haven't actually hard-coded with an elif condition in this case,
帕德玛应该住在什么样的房子里。
what house Padma is meant to be in.
事实证明，还有其他方法可以实现这一点。
Well, it turns out there's other ways to implement this.
事实上，这里有一些冗余，在那里
Indeed, there's some redundancy here, in that
我们在查哈利，赫敏，罗恩是不是都在格兰芬多。
we're checking if Harry, or Hermione, or Ron are all in Gryffindor.
我觉得我们至少可以把代码收紧一点,
I feel like we can at least tighten this code up a little bit,
使用我们已经见过的技术。
using techniques we've seen already.
所以让我来做这个。
So let me go ahead and do this.
让我上去做这样的事情。
Let me go up here and instead do something like this.
让我们摆脱这两个小精灵,
Let's get rid of these two blocks of elifs,
暂时离开哈利家。
leaving just Harry's for a moment.
让我们再次使用“或”关键字，并说或名称
And let's use that "or" keyword again, and say or name
等于引号，赫敏，或者名字等于引号，罗恩,
equals equals quote, unquote Hermione, or name equals quote, unquote Ron,
这样就可以把三个案子合并成一个
thereby consolidating all three cases, if you will, into just one
如果声明。
if statement.
那我们还有一个单独的精灵给德拉科，因为他不是,
Then we still have a separate elif for Draco because he's not,
事实上，在格兰芬多。
in fact, in Gryffindor.
然后是最后一个能抓住其他人的人。
And then the final else to catch anyone else.
现在让我继续运行该程序的这个版本: house.py 的 Python。
Let me go ahead now and run this version of the program, Python of house.py.
这次我输入赫敏。
I'll type in Hermione this time.
她也还在格兰芬多。
She, too, is still in Gryffindor.
让我和罗恩试试。
Let me try it with Ron.
这一点似乎也是正确的。
And that, too, still seems to be correct.
事实证明还有另一种方法也许可以
Well, it turns out there's another approach altogether that can perhaps
使您的代码不那么冗长。
make your code a little less verbose.
你可以想象这个代码有多复杂
You could imagine how complicated this code might
如果我们不是只有哈利，赫敏和罗恩，而是一大群人
get if we had not just Harry, and Hermione, and Ron, but a whole bunch
还有其他的名字，格兰芬多，Slytherin，以及所有的名字
of other names as well, for Gryffindor, for Slytherin, and for all
其他霍格沃茨的房子。
of the other Hogwarts houses.
所以你可以想象这些代码会变得非常笨拙，非常快。
So you could imagine that code just getting pretty unwieldy pretty fast.
事实证明，你可以用另一种方法
Well, it turns out another technique you can
使用的确是这个叫做“匹配”的关键词，在精神上非常相似,
use is, indeed, this keyword called match, which is very similar in spirit,
但语法不同。
but the syntax is different.
它允许你更简洁地表达同样的想法。
And it allows you to express the same ideas a little more compactly.
那就让我回 House 吧 Py。
So let me go back to house.py.
让我提议我去掉现在的 if，elif，else 方法,
And let me propose that I get rid of my current if, elif, else approach,
而不是这样做。
and instead do this.
字面上使用关键字 match，然后键入变量的名称,
Literally use the keyword match, and type the name of the variable,
或价值，我们希望匹配。
or value, that we want to match on.
然后我将继续，包括一个结肠。
And then I'm going to go ahead and include a colon.
然后在下面，我会包括，真的,
And then underneath that, I'm going to include, literally,
一个叫 case 的关键词。
a keyword called case.
我要考虑的第一个案子就是哈利。
And the first case I want to consider is going to be Harry.
我要把哈利放在引号里，因为它是一根绳子或者一个搅拌器。
And I'm going to put Harry in quotes, because it's a string or a stir.
在这一行的末尾还有一个冒号。
And I'm going to have another colon at the end of this line.
在这个下面缩进了，我要继续了，现在,
And indented under that one, I'm going to go ahead and, for now,
把格兰芬多打印出来当然，那是哈利的家。
print out Gryffindor, which, of course, is Harry's house.
否则，我会有另一个案子，引用赫敏的话。
Otherwise, I'm going to have another case for quote, unquote Hermione.
同样的，在这个缩进的下面,
And similarly, I'm going to have under that indented,
引用格兰芬多的话，结束引用。
print quote, unquote Gryffindor, close quote.
现在我要给 Ron 另一个例子，也是引号，带有冒号。
Now I'm going to have another case for Ron, also in quotes, with a colon.
现在引用格兰芬多的原话。
Now print quote, unquote Gryffindor.
现在我又有了一个案子，比如说，德拉科。
And now I'm going to have a other case for, let's say, Draco.
这个更有趣，因为德拉科，当然,
This one gets a little more interesting because Draco, of course,
现在是在 Slytherin。
now is in Slytherin.
然后我会继续，暂时就这样。
And then I'm going to go ahead and leave it as that for now.
让我继续保存这个文件回到我的终端窗口,
So let me go ahead and save this file, and go back down to my terminal window,
运行 Python of house.py，Enter。
running Python of house.py, Enter.
我们试试哈利吧。
And let's go ahead and try Harry.
他好像还在格兰芬多。
And he seems still to be in Gryffindor.
再给赫敏放一遍，回车。
Let's run it again for Hermione, Enter.
格兰芬多。
Gryffindor.
我们跳到德拉科，输入德拉科的名字。
Let's skip ahead to Draco, and type in Draco's name.
他确实在 Slytherin。
He is, indeed, in Slytherin.
现在让我们试试另一个我们还没处理过的名字
Now let's try another name that we haven't handled
像帕德玛一样的情况再次出现。
a case for, like Padma again, Enter.
我们只是被忽视了。
And we're just ignored.
没有任何输出，因为没有帕德玛的案子。
There's no output whatsoever because there wasn't a case for Padma.
当然，现在我们可以回过头来明确地为 Padma 加一个。
Now we could, of course, go back in and explicitly add one for Padma.
但是如果我们，类似于 else 结构,
But what if we, similarly to the else construct,
只是想要一个处理任何名字没有明确指定的人的概括？
just want a catchall that handles anyone whose name is not explicitly specified?
根据这个新的 match 语句的语法,
Well, turns out the syntax for that, using this new match statement,
就是还有一个案子，然后用
is to still have another case, but then to use
这个单一的下划线字符，在 Python 的其他上下文中使用。
this single underscore character, which is used in other contexts in Python.
但在这里，它意味着无论什么案子还没有处理,
But for here, it's meant to say whatever case has not yet been handled,
打印出来，就像我们之前做的那样,
go ahead and print out, as we did before, for instance,
引号，引号，谁，最后加个问号。
quote, unquote who, with a question mark at the end.
现在让我们继续并重新运行 house.py 的 Python。
Now let's go ahead and rerun this Python of house.py.
我再打一遍帕德玛的名字。
I'll type Padma's name again.
这次，我想我们至少要去
And this time, I think we're at least going
得到一个明确的响应，指出是谁,
to get an explicit response indicating who,
而以前我们没有这样的等价物。
whereas previously we did not have the equivalent of that.
现在，我觉得我们倒退了一点。
Now, I think we've regressed a little bit.
我们把哈利和赫敏从紧凑的关系中解放出来,
We went from tightening things up by putting Harry, and Hermione,
和 Ron 都在同一行的 if 语句中。
and Ron all on the same line in the same if statement.
但是这里，我们现在有三个案例陈述，同样，对于所有三个
But here, we have now three case statements, again, for all three
那些。
of those.
我们也可以加强这个代码。
Well, we can tighten this code up, as well.
但是语法会有点不同。
But the syntax is going to be a little bit different.
我要删除赫敏和罗恩的这两个中间案例。
I'm going to go ahead and delete these two middle cases for Hermione and Ron.
然后这里，哈利的名字旁边，冒号前面,
And then up here, next to Harry's name, before the colon,
我要用一根竖直的杆，然后
I'm going to go ahead and use a single vertical bar, and then
引用赫敏的话。
a quote, unquote Hermione.
然后再来一小节，引用罗恩的话。
Then another single bar and do quote, unquote Ron.
这就是如何使用这个相对较新的匹配语句,
And this is how, using this relatively new match statement,
你可以说相当于哈利，或赫敏，或罗恩,
you can say the equivalent of Harry, or Hermione, or Ron,
但比使用 if 语句更简洁
but more concisely than you could using an if statement
单独使用，正如我们以前实现的那样。
alone, as we implemented it previously.
现在，使用 house.py 的 Python 对该程序进行最后一次运行。
So now, one final run of the program with Python of house.py.
确保哈利还在格兰芬多。
Let's make sure that Harry is still in Gryffindor.
确保赫敏还在格兰芬多。
Let's make sure that Hermione is still in Gryffindor.
我们得确保罗恩还在格兰芬多。
Let's make sure that Ron is still in Gryffindor.
事实上，他们三个都是。
And indeed, all three of them are.
现在，一如既往地使用 Python 和更一般的编程,
Now, as always with Python and programming more generally,
你可以用不同的方法来解决这些问题。
there's going to be different ways you can solve these problems.
这只是您工具箱中的另一个工具。
This is just another tool in your toolkit.
可以说，它已经让事情变得更加紧张。
Arguably, it has tightened things up.
可以说，它可能更易读一些
Arguably, it's perhaps a little more readable
因为语法比较简单,
because there's a little less syntax going on,
少一点等号和 elif 的重复,
a little less duplication of equal signs and elif,
到处都是 Elif 和 Elif。
and elif, and elif all over the place.
但归根结底，这将是解决同一问题的同样正确的方法。
But ultimately, this would be an equally correct approach to that same problem.
但结果证明，你的匹配声明
But it turns out with a match statement you
也可以进行更强大的匹配。
can do even more powerful forms of matching, as well.
在这里，我们只是用它来实现与 if，elif 相同的思想,
Here, we've used it simply to implement the same idea as that if, elif,
else 构造。
else construct.
值得一提的是，如果你用其他语言编程,
And it's worth noting, if you've programmed in some other language,
这里的语法确实是正确的。
the syntax here is, indeed, correct.
例如，您不需要 break 语句,
You do not need, for instance, a break statement,
就像撒满了胡椒粉一样。
as has been peppered throughout.
你不需要什么默认值，或者什么明确的东西。
And you don't need something like default, or something explicit.
实际上，您只需在比赛结束时使用这个下划线作为总括。
You, indeed, just use this underscore as your catchall at the end of the match.
只要加入一些新的关键词
So just by adding in some of these new keywords
这里，比如 if 和 elif，还有 else，我们现在有能力
here, like if, and elif, and else, we have now the ability
提出有关价值观的问题。
to ask questions about values.
我们有能力分析来自用户的输入,
We have the ability to analyze input from users,
并最终做出决定。
and ultimately make decisions about it.
还有这些条件句。
And these, then, where our conditionals.
我们不仅可以使用函数,
Lying ahead is going to be the ability for us to not only use functions,
和变量，还有这些条件,
and variables, and also these conditionals,
而且，下一步，循环——现在，一次又一次做某事的能力。
but also, next, loops-- the ability to do something, now, again and again.